hello welcome it's December
19th
2024 we're in our fourth quarterly
Roundtable for the year so welcome to
the active inference Institute we're a
participatory online Institute that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference this is
recorded in an archive live stream so
please provide feedback and super chats
live chats so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live
stream everything at the Institute is
participatory so head over to active
inference do Institute to get involved
and check out our updated
site this slide has a lot of stable
links which you can go to as an entry
point
and we'll always keep these stable links
updated even as their underlying targets
evolve so that you can have some stable
reference and entry points into
it okay this is our fourth quarterly
Round Table of the year it is close to
the end of the year we've done a
quarterly Round Table every quarter
since the beginning of
2021 so we're approaching 16 a t of
TS Alex and blue co- officers of the
year would you like to say hello and
anything
else hi happy
2024 happy end of 2024 I'm excited about
all the things that the Institute has
done this year and about all the changes
that are happening in transitions um
that we're looking forward next
year uh yeah hi uh and this remind me
how it started now we Institute but I
remember how it was a coms group in just
online format without even possibly
knowing names or
faces but from from the beginning
understand that active
inference uh approach and principles
could help us to grow into something
great thank you yes teamc 2020 active
flab 21 Institute
22 all right let's continue on first at
The Institute scale all right one of the
major highlights of this year being the
second version snapshot release of the
sort of Keystone publication active
inference ecosystem and Institute one
way or the other and the first version
of this publication we did also in a
great collaborative team in
2023 this year we dipped back in we
started with where we left off
as any updater would and took it in a
ton of different
directions ecosystem. Active inference
do Institute is the entry point and just
to give a bit of the anatomy of the
document and show a few of the pages
some of the nested memes for nested
themes at the top level this living
documents or production has an
abstract a list of authors a single page
on active
inference a closing discussion and two
main body sections one on the Institute
and one on the
ecosystem about the Institute the
subsections include history Mission
Vision Values and principles our Focus
areas some of our
directions
strategy the organization of The
Institute
Communications and other topics
about the
organization under that if you unfold
that tick mark you'll see the formal
morphology for example the scientific
Advisory board board of directors
officers members the organizational
units administrative functions the edu
active education functions the Reiner
research functions and then a variety of
programs that we have at The Institute
such as volunteer internship mentorship
so on and some having begun in the
beginning others being
incipient in The Institute project
section there's a roster of projects
different types different stages all
entry points so what what is happening
what what has happened these are some of
the things that have happened
right very here on the ecosystem
side the sections include the priorities
and the challenge areas for the broader
space the fields where people are really
out there applying active inference and
adjacent
techniques we're starting to explore how
we think about the development of the
ecosystem about how to curate and stay
on top of the different projects that
are out
there past present and future likely
overwhelmingly not at the
Institute however we see a lot of value
and meaning in having domain experts and
domain curious contributors who
contribute in a really
nuanced way for example to a certain
field or
subfield having something like an
ongoing research report or meta analysis
of different approaches for example in
robotics and those sorts of sector
reports can be great links to share for
onboarding for starting with somebody
who wants to enter into active inference
and their field of reference also it
could support research students people
who are applying or thinking about
entrepreneurship or startups in
different areas so those are some of the
pages and one of the big jumps this year
compared to last year last year we wrote
it linearly in a Google doc this year we
went full nested collaborative style and
while it takes some time to get your
fractal legs running it's going to
enable a lot of very expressive ways for
us to collaborate and compose and
translate and generate documents so
overall it's awesome to have a team have
a lot of eyes on different parts of the
document and for the process and the
product to
be made
for people to use it so we hope that you
enjoy diving around
that document Alex or blue any comments
on
that yeah I think that's is a really um
you know neat transition from the linear
Google doc to the interactive Koda and
it reminds me like of um like a Wiki
right like a working Wiki a living
breathing Wiki document like when we
were at SFI the project Wiki that
everyone had and everyone could
contribute to I think that putting the
Institute projects there is really you
know nice and helpful so you can kind of
see what's going on and when was this
page last updated and and all of those
um all those things so I think as a
living document this is a a good place
for it a nice a nice
home and even though it's only our
second versioned snapshot first off now
we can make many more micro edits along
the year and then making the
snapshotting a lot more simple
and it's already become something I look
forward to in terms of our nested time
scales and the annual and slower maybe
we'll have a decade scale
snapshots okay another major highlight
from the end of this year on November
13th 14th and 15th was the fourth
applied active inference
Symposium this was quite an event there
were 3 days of activities the first two
days had two Mega streams the third day
with John clippinger and the biofirm
project leading a a workshop on Biore
Regional active inference and
AI there was a team of co-organizers so
it was great to work with people on on
different fronts
including people who were co-organizers
as well as presenters there was 30 plus
hours of people sharing what was
happening this year in applied Act of
inference which is coming truer and
truer to what this Symposium has always
been about not that application is the
only thing out there but people are
always asking and wanting to know how
how and where and why
and what about doing active inference
and this brought
together a lot of presenters from around
the world who are sharing where they're
at on those
Journeys and the tools and the
approaches and everything along the way
so I look forward to the Symposium for
2025 it's never too early to begin if
someone's interested in joining we can
begin with a template and some of the
notes that we used this year we can work
with a local partner possibly to explore
some kind of inperson activities
regionally we'd be very interested in
some sponsors or other partners who
might like to support the open science
publishing element or any other number
of things so it's not too early if
you're interested in the Symposium or
you thought it was cool or you thought
there was something that could be
updated or improved or that it's its
reach or impact could be magnified let's
do that next
year any comments on the
Symposium all right now into some
updates about different programs and
different
Personnel about the research
fellows program research fellows are
individuals affiliated with the
Institute reflecting the alignment of
their research and our open science
approach this was a new program we began
this year so still counts to include it
in our year end review and also in the
fourth quarter we added two new research
fellows David blumen and Robert
Warden we will be in contact with all
the fellows hearing about how we can
support them best for the coming year
one exciting Avenue is that the Donate
link supports the project restricted
donations and so fellows we hope will be
in a position to
receive donations to their project and
then
have the ability to decide how those are
used in service the project with the
oversight and a streamlined overhead
from The Institute side so we hope that
we can provide that kind of formal
Financial organizational support to
research fellows possibly eventually
much more than that and also work more
closely next year with the scientific
Advisory Board and with interns to to
Really accelerate their projects the
next round of review of fellows will be
sometime in
2025 we will continue
to entertain research fellow
applications different areas of active
inference research all welcome and also
explore what what other kinds of fellows
might be act like in education or
otherwise so welcome to David and Robert
and thanks again to JF Anna and John for
pioneering this program and for their
very unique agendas any comments on
this it's just been awesome to um you
know have participate really Anna has
led some um interactive like sessions
and that was been awesome to participate
in over the last year and um also was
great to um meet David in IRL IRL that
was really nice so I'm looking forward
to uh what these guys are going to turn
out and um who who comes on board next
what's the next cohort look
like all
right to our science ific Advisory Board
we had our largest
Sab
yet
Sab was introduced in
2022 as a way to get scientific guidance
not just you know pouring colored
liquids into beakers and all of that but
thinking more broadly about education
research and ways that science is being
done in the modern context so it's an
awesome set of of individuals and we
thank them all in their various levels
of contribution from Little to
major in
2025 we'll be focusing the
Sab coordinating it with the nested
temporal rhythms at The
Institute providing clearer
opportunities for feedback with the
fellows and the interns people on the SA
a lot of insight to give fellows and
interns could use that so we hope that
there will be Synergy amongst those
programs we'll also be looking to the
Sab members for their evaluation of
project proposals and measurements
understanding what kinds of projects and
which directions to engage
in we'll be looking for guidance around
the institutes scientific and
educational strategy overall and their
collaboration on specific components of
our development related to open science
dii and more so go to sa. active
inference do Institute if you're
interested it's not required to be a
published expert in active inference
specifically sap includes science more
generally so for those who feel like
they could be that curious and brave
contributor in the room if they feel
like they could help make make proposals
and projects more legible by asking
basic questions if they feel like they
could contribute a scientific domain
expertise then we would welcome your
application and we'll look to have that
in by January
15th any comments Alex or
blue okay thank you to our officers all
present here and to our board of
directors officers are at the more
tactical and the faster scale while we
look to continue to learn organizational
formal
procedures and work with the board of
directors to have that level of formal
oversight and
governance in the beginning of next year
will be electing the next cohort of the
board of directors so do consider
applying especially if you have
experience in any of these areas like
nonprofits or
below about
Partnerships Partnerships are structured
relationships between the Institute and
other organizations who are aligned and
are looking to make meaningful visible
imp impactful contributions to the
active inference open source
ecosystem who are looking to upskill and
accelerate their own processes of
learning and
application organizations who are
looking to connect with our community
and the growing
field possibly Partners who are looking
to form a regional or language or sector
or domain level
collaboration and also provide critical
input to The Institute and question mark
and
Beyond the second half of this year was
marked by the addition of well first
this program arising in 2024 which is
cool and a second partner joining Newman
games thinking a lot about active
inference in and for
games uh and also some Discord
fun with our partner first principles
first we've coordinated on aspects of
organizing the Symposium and some other
activities as well so there's a lot of
ways that we look to develop this
out if
you're applying active inference in a
company or you're thinking about doing
so or not this could be a very
interesting opportunity and we we will
as as with all things continue to update
it based on how our Niche responds and
and reflects back these
affordances Alex or
blue
okay also in big 2024 news was the
recognition of our 501c3 tax exempt
status as a nonprofit in the US
we aim to develop our philanthropy
program and endowment over the
years as we develop from our current all
volunteer status on through something
that's larger and more sustainable for
people's time and reflects the the
relevance of what they're
doing please head over to donate. active
inference Institute if you feel like
making such a donation or get in touch
if you have any other custom
considerations uh if you if you'd like a
uh conversation about where that could
go we would look forward to it
as we
deeply respect the Priceless ways that
people attend to the work and think it
could go much much much
much bigger and faster not that size and
speed are everything but with financial
support Alex or blue do you have any
comments was beautifully
put truly I do not like to dilute our
actim semantics with financialization so
I hope that we can find the right kinds
of supports through Grant and
philanthropy and so on that allow us to
just pitch that fast ball and call those
shots and have the opportunity for
people to provide crowdsourced support
of of many kind but really hold up the
the Priceless meaning of attention while
also keeping
it compliant and sustainable and
reasonable organizationally and again as
alluded to in the fellows page you can
go to that link and drop down to make a
project restricted donation which we can
now account for so those donations will
have a reasonable Institute level
overhead percentage taken the rest will
be available to the project for whatever
they feel like is going to facilitate
the work and it's a cool way to support
specific projects or let us know if you
want to support a specific project
that's not here right
now
okay okay some quick updates from the
organizational
units first on edu
active so we had four main projects this
year all of which will submit in due
time their measurements and re prepare
for next year active inference ontology
audio visual production text group
activities in the active inference
Journal just briefly on the textbook
group this is working through and
sharing an epistemic Niche around the
2022 active inference
textbook still the only textbook out
there but likely not for
long cohort 6 finished earlier this year
cohort 7 will continue from the midpoint
on in
2025 and
as with all things this is a volunteer
activity so if somebody wants to see a
time zone an open
discussion application oriented sessions
if somebody wants to describe or
facilitate in live sessions if somebody
wants to make asynchronous contributions
like augmenting or cleaning up questions
the hundreds of questions that are
written in the document if somebody
wants to explore translating parts of
this open- Source textbook or our open
source materials around it there's a ton
of ways to get involved so like if
you're listening just jump in and let's
do it because there's a lot of people
reading the book and there'll be more
Learners in the time to come so there's
never been a better time to increase the
opportunities for others in terms of
synchronous and asynchronous active
education and also we will continue to
template other reading groups and other
educational material because as the
years passed by now it'll be almost 3
years since this textbook coming out in
March
22 that has opened up so many other
avenues for learning so we will continue
to hold the space for this 2022 textbook
while also seeing it kind of like an
attractor or Nexus where a lot of other
resources get brought in a lot of other
things can happen there
too um just on the textbook group uh I
think that the math learning group this
year that was um done by octopus was
such a big like um augmentation for for
the textbook group so um shout out to
octopus for facilitating that for us
that was super helpful um and just I I
want to comment on the amount of
annotation like just I remember like the
first cohort of the textbook group um
like being you know before the formulas
were there before I mean you know being
among the first to to do any kind of
annotation for the textbook um versus
the amount of annotation that's there
now is like seriously seriously
impressive and it's um amazing and
awesome to see like the result of so
much collaborative co-learning um in
like a tangible form so the coda page is
really quite awesome and deep and has
evolved a lot over these
years how many people
currently for cohort including cohort 7
was
involved at least a bit into learning
active
inference that's a great question the
number of registrations over summed over
all the cohorts is in below hundreds
like probably between 3 and
500 and the number of people joining one
to many meetings is probably in the few
to several
dozens
that it's dozens of people who have come
through all the videos are available um
of the of recordings and and subsets of
those people and also people who
probably never joined a synchronous
activity maybe even people who didn't
register and still made use of the
resources the the YouTube views and
comments and discussions and all this
other work so it's just so interesting
with this sort of open science and
reading group where it's like
both being in the
spotlight in terms of it being recorded
in the Seminary
as well as not knowing what's out
there nevertheless
though in audiovisual production where
we coordinate the live streams and
podcasts we had a great year tomorrow
Dean and I are going to do a 2024 review
stream so we'll go over at least in a
cursory
quick gloss the 137 videos that were
happening this year
2024 um to to recap some of the the hits
these are the most po popular uploaded
videos on our
page commonality being
darius's
Insight series being immensely popular
with the exception
of other videos with Carl friston and
the course overview for the physics of
information processing with Chris
Fields
insights took took the leaderboard so
epic work Darius this was an amazing
series for the most popular live streams
Chris Field's course lecture one 2 3
four five and six in that order
interestingly so it's like there's the
attrition rate right there as well as
the model stream with Ryan
Smith live stream with Jonathan gour
which is pre-aging some of the
connections between the wol from area
and active inference and and other cool
work like this osum so for people who
are skilled
or not yet but might like to be with any
number of ways to help like suggesting
and curating and inviting guests
facilitating streams and videos in
English and other
languages improving social media posting
and other ways to communicate before
during and after videos these are all
places where somebody doesn't need to
know how to derive variational free
energy to make truly unique impact on
the availability of these
materials all right to
Reiner so from The Institute side we had
several projects in
Reiner the most active was our RX and
fur. JL Learning and Development Group
around the Julia package for statistics
and active inference RX
infer we continued to explore a few
Avenues around knowledge
engineering and on the software
development side in active blocker and
active INF France had a lot of
fun just about the RX and fur
project we had many people join those
enjoyable Discord times including this
morning but
Thursdays this year and the the the
meetings notes tell
Tales we applied for two grants as a
team to to support and catalyze the work
that a bunch of people are involved in
we have one Grant still pending it's
published though as a pre-print on Farm
Works do decentralized AI agents for
personalized Solutions working with
Vladimir bin and collaborators so this
is going to be an uncertainty to be
resolved in early
2025 something that ties in well with a
lot of other projects though so we look
to continue this and just a few days ago
we learned that we did not receive a AI
safety Grant Village validating
inference for large scale agent
governance
ecosystems so so if you're a grant
officer or a philanthropist you're
interested in AI safety if you want to
contribute if you want to support we
have a lot of people interested in those
topics we and others believe that active
inference has a unique role to play in
the AI safety and Alignment space so
maybe get in
touch a little bit more generally about
projects at The
Institute we're going to take two passes
at the prepare measure
cycle here in the center we have a
holographic screen markof blanket
boundary interface all that and there's
a cycle of preparation and
measurement interfacing with that screen
by Alice and Bob on both sides and in
the context of projects at The Institute
that's reflected by a prepare form and a
measure form the measure form has a
short version that basically just says
what was it what happens can we share it
and there's a longer version so now
zooming out a little bit preparation
lets us know that you're about to start
something it might be something that
doesn't ask anything of The Institute
it's just like hey list this publicly or
don't but I'm about to go out or maybe
there's something small or even
something very large that the Institute
could do to support what you're
proposing to do or there's something
that's blocking your fulfillment of that
but you'd like to propose it pending
possibly a future moment when we have an
internal grants program so that applies
to every measurement from the icade on
up to the the
multi- sensor
collaboration and on the measurement
side it is about what happened it could
be I saw a bird it could be I saw two
birds it could be I saw this paper I
didn't write it but I came across this
paper it could be here's what we did in
our project and here's what we learned
and these preparation and measurement
forms are some of the primary interfaces
amongst
everyone all those listening and
attending and The Institute it's a
standard that we hold Institute internal
projects too as well that they engage in
this alternating two-stroke engine of
reporting back even if it's just one
sentence but it's truly amazing how much
Challenge and friction and inertia there
can be around reporting even when people
have done truly incredible things so
gently and kindly to myself and others I
encourage that people fill out that
measurement form when they've done stuff
so that we can share it if you say yes
in the newsletter and through other
channels and so that it can be broader
understood what you're doing so that you
can demonstrate when you did certain
things and it's an important channel of
communication with the
Institute there was a bunch of projects
that fulfilled the proposed and some
measurements this year uh they're all
available at activities. active infera
Institute and all of those projects will
go inactive at the end of this
year they will be required to fill out a
measurement form and a proposal to come
back online in
24 that will support the flow of energy
and attention and activity to
live projects so that we can have
healthy portfolio scale updating and
continue to to reenter The Institute as
a place where people can find out what's
going on find out what has been find out
what could be get visibility for their
work meet others so again measure for
providing any updates or
observations it could just be oneoff it
could be anonymous also for projects
it's required for internships and so
on and prepare so if you're proposing a
new Endeavor or a new project whether
you would like it
listed at our activities page for
visibility or whether you're seeking
some further kind of support and
ask big we would be honored and excited
to curate those requests and
dream of a future day when we could
share
that with the Sab or with funders or
with other groups and say Here's what
people are proposing here's the kind of
support that we would want to provide to
support these people to do this work
this way and here's how we'll have
accountability and follow up with the
measurements too so just some thoughts
of course open for everyone's
co-creating and feedback and and joining
from there but those are just some of
the ways that we've seen how this
prepare and measure two-stroke
engine can help
us do more
together Alex or blue any thoughts on
projects or just anything else also 2024
being the year that we introduced this
two-stroke cycle of prepare and measure
following from the 2023 course but do
you have any thoughts on
that yeah I like it the prepared measure
um way of of just reporting I think it's
really hard for a lot of people to toot
their own horn you know especially in
science I think like it's hard for
people to like self-promote or it's not
not something scientists are necessarily
like naturally inclined to do um but I
think having this reporting mechanism
helps us like to track what's actually
happening so like if you didn't document
it you didn't do it essentially um so it
is a good way to kind of look back and
and um you know see your own
Achievements not just not just for us
but but for
yourself yeah and I think that's a great
example what I usually try to do is to
apply uh
new new
theoretical
developments some specific ways of doing
so we're taking it serious and trying to
implement in some aspects of what we're
doing and yeah it's really great that
it's like from heavy heavy scientific
Quantum
curse goes into some actually possibly
cont intuitive but actually small
steps for project to to prepare and to
measure and it's gives
um effects brings effects not only for
project itself but the whole nested
structure of our organization and even
for ecosystem as we understand it
currently thank you yeah blue to your
point about toting horns I think a great
role informally or possibly for an
intern or for a project scale is like an
internal reporter role or documentarian
orograph role someone who's just like
that was an awesome meeting I'm going to
spend a few minutes summarizing that
authentically just by hand or I'm going
to use llms to summarize that and
distill that into a report and and
there's so many ways in which like the
people who
are still accelerating up their learning
curve in a given meeting can be making
those reports and asking those questions
and not just be included in the culture
but actually creating it so that's
cool
okay a closing
section towards a stack for applying Act
of
inference just some quick notes and
thoughts a lot more will unfold in the
coming year but I just wanted to
footnote it in
24 and uh point a little bit towards
some of the ways that that this may be
going during this section anyone please
feel free to write comments or questions
in live chat and then after this section
will have any final thoughts or comments
from Alex and blue and then look at any
questions in in the live chat and
address them from there
okay whether when what how for for the
institute for active inference
overall whether to actively infer or not
that is the question whether is nobler
in the mind to suffer the slings and
arrows of subject matter expertise or
take mathar arms against a sea of
uncertainties and by expertly predicting
bound and live with
them when are we going to be doing that
well always already sure and still we're
going to be doing it next year in 2025
and we hope much beyond that too and as
all I think therefore I am I am
therefore I think type systems which we
study as long as it's actively inferred
to
be so what really is it what is
happening at the
Institute we want to support host
convene resource provision active
inference research education and service
forms and functions
for modeling ecosystems of shared
intelligence across many domains
those projects will always be scattered
and volatile across different
developmental
stages we will aim to stay relevantly
updated with developments from outside
the Institute about research companies
tools and other happenings and we'll
look to curate and analyze those reports
of measurements into sector reports
language reports all different ways to
make the information more accessible
but what is it really well beyond our
core educational and open science
infrastructural work like the ontology
Journal textbook groups and so on there
is a growing Cadre of projects that are
developing different applications of
active inference so these are like
domain or system of Interest scale or
user space applications for different
aspects of systems where AI has or
hasn't been applied but people are
thinking about it differently with
active inference and that includes
projects and call signs like the biofirm
for regenerative Finance Biore
regionalism like farmworks for
agriculture and iot Village for AI
safety and a variety of other projects
from the legal domain The mological
Domain in the area of cognitive security
science ific ecosystem modeling Regional
modeling and all these other kinds of
projects that research fellows bring to
the table so there's all these projects
when people think what would it really
look like would it be a car is it a
drone is it Precision Psychiatry is it
resource allocation in servers what are
those Frontline applications of active
inference and so these projects can be
nurtured
on top of a robust applicable accessible
how that's what people asked in the
active inference Symposium was okay
applied how and how is a key part of
getting these projects to where they can
be and where people prefer them to be
getting to that how and building the
documentation and education and
everything around it and before it is
going to continue to be a mission for us
in the years to come in this fractal
Journey with the Institute as vehicle we
see collaborators contributors co-
explorers and partners and we look
towards the development of open- source
tools which span the Continuum from here
on the left let's just call it the light
stack so this would be multimedia and
intera Ive
experiences in the no code on through
low code level of technical detail all
running in a browser or something that
doesn't require installation so these
might be variously deployed products or
websites that make graphical accessible
interfaces for active inference
possible and on the right side is the
heavy stack so this is the sour sort of
full-fledged Enterprise grade research
Integrity custom modular
stack starting at a place that's
relevant for the project so just because
I'm laying it out this way tentatively
doesn't mean that this is the entry
point for every project but digging down
down down to the bottom to the basement
of the bottom bunker we have the
possibility of running active inference
algorithms on bare metal silicon and
also other substrates already people are
working and have presented on neural
substrates and we and physical
substrates like Thermo Computing and we
can look forward to a variety of other
unconventional post Turing post Von
noyman architectures so it's important
to leave leave the bottom floor open
because we don't know the physical
embodiment of what Computing and
cognition will look like in the
future working just temporarily within a
a computational Von noyman Paradigm we
have a lot to learn from the
neuroimaging community and I'm really
thankful for Bradley Alisia and
colleagues in open science for their
contributions to the Sab and to the
Symposium and for highlighting some of
the ways in which the neuroimaging
community which is also trace it back to
Carl friston's lab the Genesis of active
inference community in certain ways the
ways that they deal deal with
reproducibility and research Integrity
for example having neurod Debian which
is a variant of the Debian Linux
distribution maybe we could have an
active Debian they have neurodes which
is a
containerization environment flexible
and scalable data analysis environment
for reproducible neuroimaging we could
have active desk a walking desk exercise
desk something like that for a
containerization so that open-source
containers and images as well as
proprietary or encrypted blobs could be
provided and we would know that it would
come to work Alex aoria in his lab has
uh through the NGC package neural uh
generative coding has a NGC mum which
reflects all the
different models that people have coded
up in in
NGC so that each paper can have its own
repo and then also those repos get
compiled into this museum for
NGC and while we have our curated
tables Morgan highlights neuro Fedora
thank you while we have our curated
tables of active inference
implementations which people can look at
and and see the the dozens of Open
Source repos
that take time to
load and see these these
repositories some of these links might
go offline or it's hard to tell where
exactly the status is or what what
attributes these different models have
what kinds of inputs or outputs are they
providing and so on and so with
something like whether Museum sounds a
little bit static or whether we want to
have some other way to to think about it
figuring out how to make generative
models and ecosystem cognitive
simulations reproducible is vital I mean
it's essential for even getting the
script to run 15 minutes later on the
same machine let alone a different
operating system or a different con
containerization environment
so I look forward to seeing the
repositories of specifications
and the rendering tools like GNN agent
maker GRT p3f come into play to finally
after all of that bring it to the
terminal inference algorithms whether
those are implemented in RX infer in PDP
whatever programming language whatever
way those inference algorithms are
implemented we could have a more total
understanding
and
customizability around going from
whatever processing substrate we're
working on through the operating system
and containerization
environment understand what version of
what generative model specification
we're working off of have reliable if
not deterministic rendering of those
generative models and strong execution
of the rendered
form this would provide the most level
of customizability and the heavy stack
would
underly the graphical experiences that
are hopefully enjoyed by so many on the
light
stack back to the educational side
whether leaning more on one or more on
the other of these two
stacks we could have examples guide
books applications all these kinds of
interfaces
available there could be educational
simulations we could repr produce the
textbook examples other textbooks we
could reproduce
papers and support templates for people
who are doing research different kinds
of simulations math getting into the
analytical details visualizations games
workspaces all these kinds of
things at the Institute level contined
development and clarification of how
these core active inference functions
can be built what are the shared
cognitive computational functions that
these different applications
need that can
be reflected on a shared Tech Tree
connected to the active inference
ontology and then understanding how that
all interfaces with different
applications will support collaboration
it'll support all these different ways
which people are thinking well how is it
going to be
applied they may want to jump in at the
Domain level or the system of
Interest knowing that there's something
solid and something that people could
also contribute to if they wanted to
underneath so it'll be exciting to see
this all unfold next year and
Beyond so thank you all for a great
tetrahedral year
2024 until the next one which of course
will be
so blue and Alex what are
your last uh thoughts or questions here
and then we'll look in the live
chat I just wonder where the Institute
will be in
2300 it will rule the world
definitely uh and
uh I want to share my like thoughts and
feelings and especially after the last
piece of presentation
of uh what project in Institute
currently I have a strong feeling that
engineering possibly will be the main
world world for next year currently it's
only in one of channels in Discord
but possibly by the end of next year or
even
earlier we will have uh organizational
unit of engineering because it looks
like educational research and not
actually with development but
engineering should be in place and
enabled somehow by organizational
structure uh because all that genetic
models all that application bi firms and
others as definitely looks like some
kind
of new entities which should burn and
grow starting from yeah from someone's
Knowledge from education from some deep
research and then going into life
through engineering
cycles and uh uh yeah possibly currently
Eric Syer
Group which I see is a project is which
is already grew Beyond just Eric sfer
but a lot of
ours initiatives and uh Frameworks that
could be in use in place for some
project
specifics that's why engineering is
a uh high level concept and uh methods
of work which uh we also understand and
putting in place
in for now project scales possibly need
to have more attention
more more developments in terms how to
use engineering methods in works of all
our
scales thank you that really makes me
reflect on how it's obvious and yet
still hits like a blast of cold air that
we need people with different
backgrounds to be involved and to
contribute the scientists and
researchers and academics have made a
lot of contributions to active inference
and also will in the time to come and
Engineers may play increasingly critical
roles in support
supporting those core functionalities
that research and application builds and
jumps off of and there's all these other
elements that that we play with bringing
in and work too to bring in like art and
cultures and it's not for
one person to see every corner of the
niche so how how we reconcile like that
finiteness of our own experiences and
affordances and
development with the
open-endedness of collective
systems and the way that we get to
assemble around the question and topic
of shared
intelligences
while manifesting that ourselves
hard to put into words
sometimes slash parts that can't be put
into words but it's all right there
and I guess everybody is just playing a
different part in
it okay Morgan thank
you love
evolve excellent ecography role meme
lives egg egg egg okay love evolve wrote
please share more Reflections visions of
eggnog graphy and especially wise anogra
in the next phase and Beyond okay if
either of you have a comment on
that feel free to make so otherwise I'll
keep that in
mind okay shareif wrote manifest AGI
we'll we'll wait another minute and see
if anyone else writes any comments or
specific
questions let's just quickly revisit
what we saw while just waiting one
minute for if anyone wants to write any
specific questions
there is a question about supporting
materials yeah in relation Facebook
group okay Morgan Morgan wrote If we are
doing a textbook reading group do you
have recommendations for supporting
materials
do you want to give any thoughts on
that
okay um possibly one part
about where a lot and a lot of materials
uh the textbook textbook textbook itself
contains a lot of references
and uh code document which enables
working of this group is also has a lot
of belief uh but possibly the main thing
here is the format of collective uh
learning action so to be with people who
also has have interest to learn active
inference and be and in this group and
participate of this
session uh and then put your own efforts
to support
uh learning path is could be much
more efficient than any our like just
material thank you Alex I posted the
resources
link here there's a table that Ali
curated that provides one possible path
but that's kind of the knowledge
engineering side is resources as nodes
and paths as walks on the graph and
throughout the hundreds of questions
there's so many resources and things and
somebody who is adding more fastidiously
would have probably added another
several
Factor um you pointed Alex to the the
group as
resource that there's adding into
resources including with questions and
uncertainties and then there's people as
the resource in our path to
connect and also I
think it's all happening so fast so it's
even it's even funny to remark on it but
like in
2022 when we started the textbook group
around this book there was not the
generative AI
affordance today it's
almost I I see places where people are
almost people let's just say are almost
putting more synthetic content than
authentic content and there's more
people who are using llms to summarize a
paper and then someone else uses an llm
you know so it's like of course we can
go into that forever but in terms of how
that has changed what a resource
means whereas the static resource
concept was like oh this is an awesome
stream by ramstead at all or you should
check out the paper or go to the
bibliography from there or go to a
scholar search and find out what else is
happening from that author or keyword
that kind of like Library
science all of a sudden has evolved into
the library being like the
zoo of Dreams and Nightmares where you
walk in with your
query
and living artifacts come to meet you
and so that is just
pre-transformed appropriately with
Transformers and everything like that
the landscape of learning and resources
in in ways that that have really complex
short and long-term
effects because you're only
one sentence away from please write me
an explanation of variational free
energy starting from XYZ in the style of
ABC it's like with that at everybody's
fingertips now it is trained on some of
those resources and all of that so again
not to go too much into it but
just there are so many angles of
approach that people take into active
inference and so many things that people
are looking to do with it and that would
also un unfold through that person's
Journey over the years that it's
like it's and there's such a daunting
amount now taken to the infinite
generative
level that it's really like wo what are
the right ways to learn but in that
openness around the the ways to learn
and apply that's where we
have our
work in the uncertainty around it not in
the certainty around how to learn and
apply
okay thank you Alex thank you
blue thank you to other live Chatters
and viewers
so this video should have the
information that you can use and if not
just get in touch whenever it
is okay
bye for